Guide to the Henry Burt Wright Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Burt Wright Papers
1728-1928
RG 40
Yale University Divinity School Library
15
(30 boxes)
The papers detail Wright's personal life and professional work. They are particularly useful for their documentation of his involvement in religious activity at Yale from 1894-1923 and in YMCA work during the first World War. Henry Burt Wright was born in New Haven, Connecticut on January 29, 1877. He received the B.A. (1898) and Ph.D. (1903) degrees from Yale University. He was a professor at Yale from 1903-1923. He was active in Christian work among university students and in the work of the YMCA during World War I. He died in Oakham, Massachusetts on December 27, 1923.
Wright, Henry B. (Henry Burt), 1877-1923
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1877 Jan 29 Born in New Haven, son of Henry Parks and Martha Burt Wright. H. P. Wright was Dean of Yale College from 1884 to 1909. HBW studied at home until entering the New Haven high school; summers were spent in Oakham, Mass.
1894-1898 B.A., Yale. He was a member of Delta Kappa Epsilon and the Skull and Bones society and was president of the Christian Association during his senior year.
1898-1903 Ph.D., Yale. While pursuing his graduate studies, Wright served as General Secretary of the Yale Y.M.C.A. from 1898 to 1901 and as Graduate Secretary from 1901 to 1903.
1901 Co-editor of Two Centuries of Christian Activity at Yale.
1903-1923 Throughout his teaching career, Wright continued to aid the work of the Yale and New Haven Y.M.C.A.'s by leading Bible study groups and serving as an advisor. He was also instrumental in the establishment of the Yale Hope Mission. Wright was active in the leadership of various student conferences and in evangelistic campaigns. He was a leading force in the formation of the Young Men's Club of Oakham, Mass. and was involved in Oakham community affairs. He was also a trustee of the Yale-in-China Association.
1903-1906 Tutor in Greek and Latin, Yale
1906-1907 Instructor in Greek and Latin
1907-1911 Assistant Professor, Roman History and Latin Literature
1907 Jul 24 Married Josephine L. Hayward. The couple was childless but opened their home to various young people whom they considered as their family.
1907-1908, 1911 Study in Europe
1911-1914 Assistant Professor, History department
1912 Seriously ill with a respiratory ailment
1914-1923 Stephen Merrell Clement Professor of Christian Methods, Yale Divinity School. Courses taught by Wright included "Personal Evangelism", "Rural Sociology", "Leadership of Voluntary Bible-study Groups" and "Religious Aspects of Student Problems". He was the leader in the establishment of a department at Yale for the training of Y.M.C.A. secretaries.
1917May-Jul Chief of Y.M.C.A. religious work at First Reserve Officers' Training Camp, Plattsburgh, N.Y.
1917 summer Taught at the Y.M.C.A. College, Springfield, Mass.
1917 Aug-1919 Jun Director of religious work for Y.M.C.A., Camp Devens, Ayer, Mass. Wright was in New Haven periodically during this time period due to illness or family and academic commitments.
1922 Editor of the Centennial Catalogue of Yale Divinity School
1923 Dec 27 Died in Oakham, Mass.
Scope and Contents
These papers provide a thorough picture of Wright's life and work and are particularly useful for their documentation of his involvement in religious activity-at Yale from 1894 to 1923 and in Y.M.C.A. work during the first World War.
Series I, Correspondence, dates from 1901 to 1925 and is divided into Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. Letters from his wife, sister and parents during times of separation give insight into the rich family life which was so important to Wright. Letters in the General Correspondence section reveal the various facets of Wright's career--his interests in Ancient History, Yale history, religious activity at Yale, Y.M.C.A. work, mission work and the community affairs and baseball team of Oakham, Mass. Wright was a disciplined man who took a personal interest in the lives of many people. His character is reflected in the substance and detail of his correspondence. Notable correspondents include John R. Mott, Robert P. Wilder, David R. Porter, Kenneth S. Latourette, Anson Phelps Stokes, E. Hershey Sneath, Charles R. Brown, George Sherwood Eddy and Robert E. Speer.
Series II consists of a topically arranged file which documents Wright's involvements and interests. Included in the file are class notes taken by Wright, notes for lectures, talks and sermons, drafts of unpublished writings, schedules, printed material and student papers. The topics range from "Studies in the Life of Christ" to "Fraternities and Secret Societies" to "Yale: School of Religion, Publicity Committee" to "Y.M.C.A.: Commission on Advance Program Among Students". This file provides valuable insight into the issues and concerns of religious work among college students during the first quarter of the 20th century. It is particularly useful in documenting the course of Christian activity at Yale and the development of the Yale School of Religion. Another large group of material documents the role played by the Y.M.C.A. during World War I.
Series III, Published Writings, consists of one box of material arranged alphabetically by title. The writings date from 1909 to 1921 and reflect Wright's interests in student religious work, Y.M.C.A. war work and Ancient History.
Series IV, Personal Items and Memorabilia is divided into five sections:
Biographical Material
Financial material related to Wright's book, Two
Centuries of Christian Activity at Yale
Material related to Josephine H. Wright
Photographs
Miscellaneous material
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1901-1925
II. Subject File
III. Published Writings, 1909-1924, n.d.
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1903-1928., n.d.
V. Addendum
Christian education; Religious education; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Young Men's Christian Associations; Authors; Educators; Brown, Charles Reynolds, 1862-1950; Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963; Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955; Porter, David R. (David Richard), 1882-1973; Sneath, E. Hershey (Elias Hershey), 1857-1935; Speer, Robert E. (Robert Elliott), 1867-1947; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Wilder, Robert P., 1863-1938; Wright, Henry B. (Henry Burt), 1877-1923; Yale University -- Religion; Yale University. Divinity School; Dwight Hall (Yale University)
- Correspondence, 1901-1925; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Family Correspondence: Letters from Wright's wife, Josephine (JHW) are followed by letters from other family members (primarily his father and sister Alice). Within these two sections the letters are arranged chronologically.
  General Correspondence: The letters are arranged chronologically with notable correspondents noted on the folder headings. Undated material follows the dated material and is arranged alphabetically by the sender of the letter.
  - Correspondence: Family
    - Josephine Hayward Wright (wife), 1909 Feb-Mar (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - JHW, 1909 Jul (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - JHW, 1909 Aug-Nov (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - JHW, 1909 Dec-1910 Apr (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - JHW, 1910 May-Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - JHW, 1910 Aug (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - JHW, 1910 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - JHW, 1910 Dec-1911 Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - JHW, 1911 Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - JHW, 1915 Dec-1916 Aug (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - JHW, 1916 Sep-1917 Mar (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - JHW, 1917 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - JHW, 1917 Jul-Sep (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - JHW, 1917 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - JHW, 1918 Jan-May (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - JHW, 1918 Jun-Sep (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - JHW, 1918 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - JHW, 1919 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - JHW, 1919 Apr-Nov (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Family of HBW, 1908-1909 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Family of HBW, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Family of HBW, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Family of HBW, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: General
    - Incl. to/from Richard C. Morse, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Incl. to/from Richard C. Morse and re: Federation of Graduate Clubs, 1902-1904 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Incl to/from Anson Phelps Stokes, 1905-1908 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Incl. to/from E. Hershey Sneath, Kenneth S. Latourette, 1909 Jan-Aug (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Various, 1909 Sep-Dec (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Incl. to/from Robert E. Speer, 1910 Jan-Jul (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Various, 1910 Aug-Dec (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Incl. to/from K. S. Latourette, Wm. W. Borden and re: teaching of Ancient History in various U.S. universities, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Incl. to/from Louis J. Bernhardt, John R. Mott, Chas. D. Hurrey, 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Incl. to/from J. R. Mott, A.P. Stokes, David R. Porter, Frank Knight Sanders, G. S. Eddy, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Incl. to/from Louis J. Bernhardt, Henry Blodgett, G. S. Eddy, 1915 Jan-Jul (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Incl. to/from F. K. Sanders, L.Bernhardt, J. R. Mott, 1915 Aug-Dec (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Incl. to/from F. K. Sanders, J. R. Mott, 1916 Jan-Apr (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Incl. to/from E. Hershey Sneath, 1916 May-Jun (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Incl. to/from E. Hershey Sneath, K. S. Latourette, Clarence P. Shedd, 1916 Jul-Dec (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Incl. to/from George Sherwood Eddy, Robert P. Wilder, D. R. Porter, 1917 Jan, Feb (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, A.P. Stokes, R. P. Speer, 1917 Mar-Jul (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Incl. to/from Chas. D. Hurrey, C.P. Shedd, Edw. H. Hume, J. R. Mott, 1917 Aug (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Various, 1917 Sep 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, R. P. Wilder, 1917 Sep 16-30 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Incl. to/from R.E. Speer, J. R. Mott, R. P. Wilder, K. S. Latourette, 1917 Oct 1-17 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Incl. to/from Charles R. Brown, K. S. Latourette, R. P. Wilder, 1917 Oct 18-31 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Incl. to/from C.P. Shedd, R.E. Speer, 1917 Nov 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, 1917 Nov 17-30 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Incl. to/from G. S. Eddy, R. P. Wilder, C.R. Brown, 1917 Dec (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Various, 1917 no month (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, 1918 Jan 1-14 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Various, 1918 Jan 15-30 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Various, 1918 Feb 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, 1918 Feb 16-27 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Various, 1918 Mar 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Various, 1918 Mar 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, 1918 Apr 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Incl. to/from K. S. Latourette, R. P. Wilder, 1918 Apr 16-30 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Incl. to/from E. Hershey Sneath, K. S. Latourette, D. R. Porter, R. P. Wilder, 1918 May (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Incl. to/from A.P. Stokes, D. R. Porter, R. P. Wilder, 1918 Jun (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, 1918 Jul 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, R. P. Wilder, 1918 Jul 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Incl. to/from K. S. Latourette, R. P. Wilder, 1918 Aug 1-15 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Incl. to/from J. R. Mott, 1918 Aug 16-31 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, 1918 Sep 1-14 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Incl. to/from R. P. Wilder, K. S. Latourette, Frank Buchman, 1918 Sep 16-30 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Incl. to/from K. S. Latourette, C.P. Shedd, R. P. Wilder, 1918 Oct (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Incl. to/from C.R. Brown, 1918 Nov 1-15 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Various, 1918 Nov 16-30 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Incl. to/from K. S. Latourette, 1918 Dec 1-22 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Incl. to/from J. R. Mott, R.E. Speer, A.P. Stokes, 1918 Dec 23-31 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - 1918, no month (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Incl. to/from J. R. Mott, K. S. Latourette, R. P. Wilder, 1919 Jan (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Incl. to/from C.P. Shedd, R. P. Wilder, 1919 Feb 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Incl. to/from K. S. Latourette, A.P. Stokes, E. H. Sneath, J. R. Mott, 1919 Feb 1728 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, 1919 Mar 1-15 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Incl. to/from C.R. Brown, 1919 Mar 16-31 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Incl. to/from A.P. Stokes, 1919 Apr (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Various, 1919 May (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Various, 1919 Jun-Aug (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, 1919 Sep-Oct (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, 1919 Nov-Dec (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Various, 1920 Jan-Feb (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Various, 1920 Mar-Apr (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Incl. to/from C.P. Shedd, 1920 May-Oct (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Incl. to/from C.P. Shedd, D. R. Porter, 1920 Nov-Dec (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Various, 1921 Jan-Feb (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Various, 1921 Mar-Jun (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter re: New Haven Y.M.C.A., 1921 Jul-Dec (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Incl. to/from C.P. Shedd, D. R. Porter, 1922 Jan-Feb (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Various, 1922 Mar-May (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - Incl. to/from J. R. Mott, 1922 Jun-Dec (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, 1923 Jan-Feb (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, C.P. Shedd, 1923 Mar-Apr (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Incl. to/from D. R. Porter, C.P. Shedd, 1923 May-Aug (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - Various, 1923 Sep-Dec (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - Various, 1924, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - No date A-L (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - No date M-Z (Box 11, Folder 98)
- Subject File, Series II
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. The contents of the folders are in most cases arranged chronologically.
  - A (Box 12, Folder 99)
  - The Absolute Standards of Jesus (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - Ancient History (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - Association Seminar for Student Work (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - B (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - Bible Studies for Class Leaders (Box 12, Folder 104)
  - Bible Study (Box 12, Folder 105)
  - Biographies of Missionaries (Box 12, Folder 106)
  - C (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - Catullus (Box 12, Folder 108)
  - D (Box 12, Folder 109)
  - E (Box 12, Folder 110)
  - "Enlisting for Christ and the Church" (Box 13, Folder 111)
  - "Enlisting for Christ and the Church" (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Evangelism (Box 13, Folder 113)
  - Evangelism (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - Exegesis of the New Testament (Box 13, Folder 115)
  - Expansion of Christianity (Box 13, Folder 116)
  - F (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Federation of Graduate Clubs (Box 14, Folder 118)
  - Fraternities and Secret Societies (Box 14, Folder 119)
  - Fraternities and Secret Societies (Box 14, Folder 120)
  - Fraternities and Secret Societies (Box 14, Folder 121)
  - G (Box 14, Folder 122)
  - Greek Testament (Box 14, Folder 123)
  - H (Box 14, Folder 124)
  - Horace (Box 14, Folder 125)
  - I (Box 15, Folder 126)
  - Interviewing (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - J (Box 15, Folder 128)
  - Jesus and the Problems of College Life (Box 15, Folder 129)
  - Latin Usage (Box 15, Folder 130)
  - The Layman Is Relations to Christian Work (Box 15, Folder 131)
  - M (Box 15, Folder 132)
  - Message of Jesus to the Scholar (Box 15, Folder 133)
  - Message of Jesus to the Teacher (Box 15, Folder 134)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 16, Folder 135)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 16, Folder 136)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 16, Folder 137)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 16, Folder 138)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 17, Folder 140)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 17, Folder 141)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 17, Folder 142)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 17, Folder 143)
  - The Morning Watch (Box 17, Folder 144)
  - N (Box 17, Folder 145)
  - New Haven, Church of the Redeemer (Box 17, Folder 146)
  - New Haven Y.M.C.A. (Box 17, Folder 147)
  - New Testament Greek (Box 17, Folder 148)
  - New Testament Theology (Box 18, Folder 149)
  - Oakham work (Box 18, Folder 150)
  - P (Box 18, Folder 151)
  - Parables Recorded: in Matthew (Box 18, Folder 152)
  - Pauline Epistles (Box 18, Folder 153)
  - Paul's Analysis of Love (Box 18, Folder 154)
  - Prayers (Box 18, Folder 155)
  - Principles Underlying the Leadership of Men (Box 18, Folder 156)
  - Psychology of Religion (Box 19, Folder 157)
  - Q-R (Box 19, Folder 158)
  - Religious Aspects of Student Problems (Box 19, Folder 159)
  - S (Box 19, Folder 160)
  - The School's Impress on the Political Life of the Nation (Box 19, Folder 161)
  - Student Work (Box 19, Folder 162)
  - The Student's Standards of Action (Box 19, Folder 163)
  - The Student's Standards of Action (Box 19, Folder 164)
  - Studies in the Characters and Events of Genesis (Box 19, Folder 165)
  - Studies on the Life of Christ (Box 19, Folder 166)
  - Studies on the Life of Christ (Box 19, Folder 167)
  - Studies on the Life of Paul (Box 20, Folder 168)
  - T (Box 20, Folder 169)
  - U-V (Box 20, Folder 170)
  - W (Box 20, Folder 171)
  - Wareing: The Evangelism of Jesus (Box 20, Folder 172)
  - The Will of God (Box 20, Folder 173)
  - Yale: Athletics (Box 20, Folder 174)
  - Yale: Christian Activity (Box 20, Folder 175)
  - Yale: Christian Activity (Box 20, Folder 176)
  - Yale: Christian Activity (Box 20, Folder 177)
  - Yale: College Rules (Box 21, Folder 178)
  - Yale: Contribution to Missions (Box 21, Folder 179)
  - Yale: Contribution to the Y.M.C.A. (Box 21, Folder 180)
  - Yale: Divinity School Centennial Address (Box 21, Folder 181)
  - Yale: Divinity School Centennial Catalogue (Box 21, Folder 182)
  - Yale: Divinity School, Clement Chair of Christian Methods (Box 22, Folder 183)
  - Yale: Dwight Hall (Box 22, Folder 184)
  - Yale: Evangelistic Campaigns (Box 22, Folder 185)
  - Yale: Graduate History Faculty Meeting Minutes (1915-1916) (Box 22, Folder 186)
  - Yale-in-China (Box 22, Folder 187)
  - Yale: Liquor at Class Reunions (Box 22, Folder 188)
  - Yale: Literary Cabinet (Box 22, Folder 189)
  - Yale: Miscellaneous (Box 22, Folder 190)
  - Yale: School of Religion - Miscellaneous (Box 22, Folder 191)
  - Yale: School of Religion - Pastoral Service (Box 22, Folder 192)
  - Yale: School of Religion - Printed Material (Box 22, Folder 193)
  - Yale: School of Religion - Publicity Committee (Box 23, Folder 194)
  - Yale: School of Religion - Scholarships, funding (Box 23, Folder 195)
  - Yale: School of Religion - Y.M.C.A. training (Box 23, Folder 196)
  - Yale: Student Self-Support (Box 23, Folder 197)
  - Yale: Voluntary Religious Education (Box 23, Folder 198)
  - Yale: Y.M.C.A. (Box 23, Folder 199)
  - Y.M.C.A.: Commission on Advanced Program among Student Associations (Box 23, Folder 200)
  - Y.M.C.A.: Committee on the War and the Religious Outlook (Box 23, Folder 201)
  - Y.M.C.A.: Conference on Preparatory and High School Voluntary Study (Box 24, Folder 202)
  - Y.M.C.A.: History and Polity (Box 24, Folder 203)
  - Y.M.C.A.: History and Polity (Box 24, Folder 204)
  - Y.M.C.A.: Miscellaneous (Box 24, Folder 205)
  - Y.M.C.A.: Personal Life and Relationships of the General Secretary (Box 24, Folder 206)
  - Y.M.C.A.: Student Secretaryship (Box 24, Folder 207)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - "An Army Secretary at Plattsburgh and Camp Devens" War work - see oversize material (Box 24, Folder 208)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Lists of Men (Box 25, Folder 209)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Notebooks, diary: 211 Y.M.C.A.: War work - Schedules, Maps, Printed Material (Box 25, Folder 210)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Schedules, Maps, Printed Material (Box 25, Folder 212)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Miscellaneous (Box 25, Folder 213)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Miscellaneous (Box 25, Folder 214)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Miscellaneous (Box 26, Folder 215)
  - Y.M.C.A.: War work - Miscellaneous (Box 26, Folder 216)
- Published Writings, 1909-1924, n.d.; Series III
  The writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Cantonments as Schools of Character, 1918 Mar 7 (Box 27, Folder 217)
  - Christian Activity at Yale: The Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries
  - Fighting at the Home Base, n.d.
  - Herodotus' Source for the Opening Skirmish at Plataea, 1909 (Box 27, Folder 218)
  - The Incarnation of Truth, 1911
  - The Life of the Inner Circle, 1915 (Box 27, Folder 219)
  - Personal Evangelism Among Students, 1920 (Box 27, Folder 220)
  - The Richard C. Morse Club, 1921
  - Rural Service Army Dynamics, n.d.
  - Teaching in College n.d.
  - The Will of God and a Man's Lifework (personal copy, interleaved with notes and scripture passages), 1924 (Box 27A, Folder 220A)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1910-1924; Series IV
  The material is divided into five sections:
  Biographical material - arranged chronologically
  Financial material
  Material related to Josephine H. Wright - arranged chronologically
  Photographs - arranged by subject
  Miscellaneous material
  - Biographical Material, 1903-1928, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 221)
  - Biographical Material, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 222)
  - Financial Material (Box 28, Folder 223)
  - Material Related to Josephine Wright, 1924-1928 (Box 28, Folder 224)
  - Photographs: H. B. Wright (Box 28, Folder 225)
  - Photographs: Family and friends (Box 28, Folder 226)
  - Photographs: Oakham, Mass. (Box 28, Folder 227)
  - Photographs: Y.M.C.A. War work (Box 28, Folder 228)
  - Photographs: Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 229)
  - Miscellaneous Material, 1903-1918, n.d. (Box 28, Folder 230)
  - Twelve personal scrapbooks containing material documenting Wright's life and activities (Box Ov1–Ov8)
- Addendum, Series V
  The first section of this addendum is a collection of letters from Yale graduates on the subject of religious life at Yale, ca. 1832-1883. These letters were sent to Wright in connection with his work on Two Centuries of Christian Activity at Yale 1701-1901 (New York, 1901). Also included are miscellaneous notes, advertising circulars and other papers related to the book. The correspondents are listed with their dates of birth and death.
  The second section is a collection of note cards and postcards related to Europe and European history, "made and used for Yale history courses".
  - Letters from Yale Graduates
    - Aiken, Edwin Edgerton (1859-1951) (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Aikman, Robert (1816-1900) (Box 29)
    - Allen, Arthur Huntington (1851-1923) (Box 29)
    - Alvord, Frederick (1828-1903) (Box 29)
    - Anderson, H P (Box 29)
    - Auchincloss, John Winthrop (1853-1938) (Box 29)
    - Bailey, Nathaniel Purdy (1817-1906) (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Baldwin, Simeon Eben (1840-1927) (Box 29)
    - Barnes, Henry Elbert (1832-1910) (Box 29)
    - Beach, Harlan Page (1854-1933) (Box 29)
    - Beard, Augustus Field (1833-1934) (Box 29)
    - Blodget, Henry (1825-1903) (Box 29)
    - Boomer, William Bishop (1857-1930) (Box 29)
    - Bosworth, Edward Increase (1861-1927) (Box 29)
    - Bulkley, Edwin Adolphus (1826-1907) (Box 29)
    - Burrell, Joseph Dunn (1858-1930) (Box 29)
    - Bushnell, Samuel Clarke (1852-1930) (Box 29)
    - Calkins, Wolcott (1831-1924) (Box 29)
    - Cobb, Henry Nitchie (1834-1910) (Box 29)
    - Coy, Edward Gustin (1844-1904) (Box 29)
    - Cutler, Ephraim (1832-1917) (Box 29)
    - Dana, Edward Salisbury (1849-1935) (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Day, George Edward (1815-1905) (Box 29)
    - Dill, Arthur Cushing (1857-1928) (Box 29)
    - Durand, William Cecil (1851-1918) (Box 29)
    - Dwight, Timothy (1828-1916) (Box 29)
    - Ewell, John Louis (1840-1910) (Box 29)
    - French, Joseph Richardson (1836-1913) (Box 29)
    - Furbish, Edward Brown (1837-1918) (Box 29)
    - Gilman, Daniel Coit (1831-1908) (Box 29)
    - Gilman, Edward Whiting (1823-1900) (Box 29)
    - Greene, Gardiner (1851-1925) (Box 29)
    - Hart, Burdett (1821-1906) (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Hoppin, James Mason (1820-1906) (Box 29)
    - Jessup, Henry Harris (1832-1910) (Box 29)